Kelly Cotton

PhD Candidate, Cognitive Psychology

Summary

I am currently a PhD candidate with six years experience working in research in neurology and cognitive psychology. I have experience in science writing and public outreach and have worked with a wide variety of age groups, including young children, high schoolers, and older adults.

Education

PhD, Psychology, The Graduate Center, City University of New York	Present
MA, Psychology, The Graduate Center, City University of New York	2020
BS, Brain and Cognitive Sciences, University of Rochester	2015
BA, Linguistics, University of Rochester	2015

Publications

Cotton, K. & Ricker, T.J. (2020). Working memory consolidation improves long-term memory recognition. Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition, 47(2), 208–219. doi:10.1037/xlm0000954

Cotton, K., Verghese, J., & Blumen, H. M. (2020). Gray Matter Volume Covariance Networks, Social Support, and Cognition in Older Adults. The Journals of Gerontology: Series B, 75(6), 1219-1229. doi:10.1093/geronb/gbz023

Mahoney, J. R., Cotton, K., & Verghese, J. (2019). Multisensory integration predicts balance and falls in older adults. The Journals of Gerontology: Series A, 74(9), 1429-1435. doi:10.1093/gerona/gly245

Lin, F., Ren, P., Cotton, K., Porsteinsson, A., Mapstone, M., & Heffner, K. L. (2016). Mental Fatigability and Heart Rate Variability in Mild Cognitive Impairment. The American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry, 24(5), 374-378. doi:10.1016/j.jagp.2015.12.012

Selected Presentations

Cotton, K. & Ricker, T. J. (2021, June). Consolidating a lasting memory: The role of creativity in the relationship between working memory and long-term memory. 2nd Annual Virtual Working Memory Symposium, Virtual.

Cotton, K. (2021, May). Consolidating a lasting memory. University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland.

Cotton, K. & Ricker, T. J. (2020, November). The Role of Creativity in the Relationship between Working Memory Consolidation and Long-Term Memory. Poster presented at the 61st Annual *Meeting of the Psychonomic Society, Virtual.*

Cotton, K. & Ricker, T. J. (2019, November). Working Memory Consolidation Improves Long-Term Memory Recognition in Words and Non-words. Poster presented at the 60th Annual Meeting of the Psychonomic Society, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.

Koorathota, M., Adelman, P., & **Cotton, K.** (2019, September). Project Fovea: Attention-Guided Video Production. Poster presented at the *NYC Media Lab Demo Expo*, Brooklyn, New York.

Cotton, K., Jacobs, A., Ren, P., & Lin, F. (2015, November). Mechanisms Linking Depression and Cognitive Impairment: A Systematic Review of Neuroimaging Studies. Poster presented at the *Annual Meeting of The Gerontological Society of America*, Orlando, Florida.

Fellowships, Honors, and Grants

Psychology Fellowship, The Graduate Center, CUNY	2020
Data for Public Good Fellowship, The Graduate Center, CUNY	2020
Doctoral Student Research Grant, The Graduate Center, CUNY	2020
Second Place Overall for "Project Fovea", NYC Media Lab '19	2019
Graduate Center Fellowship, The Graduate Center, CUNY	2018 - 2023
National Merit Scholar Fellowship, University of Rochester	2011 - 2015

Research Experience

Graduate Research Assistant, Memory and Attention Lab	2018 - Present
Dept. of Psychology, College of Staten Island	
Research Assistant, CREM Study	2015 - 2019

Dept. of Neurology, Albert Einstein College of Medicine

Teaching Experience

Lehman College, City University of New York Cognitve Psychology (Adjunct Instructor)

Spring 2021 - Fall 2021

City College, City University of New York

Thinking, Knowing, Remembering (Teaching Assistant)

Fall 2019 - Fall 2021

Popular Science Publications

A sweeping study shows that "brain training" games are not effective. Massive Science (2021).

Can we talk to people while they are dreaming? And can they talk back? CogBites (2021).

Our memories of shared experiences have unique neural signatures. Massive Science (2021).

Plants can grow quickly or accurately, but not both. Massive Science (2020).

Science Outreach

BioBus 2019 - Present

Mentored and supervised high school interns on semester-long experimental and science communication projects; led activities for "Saturday Science" neuroscience outreach program for families and community members

"Function" Youtube Series

2017 - Present

Served as scientific consultant and data analyst for series of videos on innovative applications of eye-tracking technology and other scientific topics